mon
sh
for
fore
for foreign
speee
uh so uh now our task is to go about in
the second turny of the wheel to figure
out what it was the Buddha really had in
mind when he talked about things
according to the mind only school what
was it that the Buddha really had in
mind when he when he taught those five
characteristics we finished the first
one which was the the fact that things
have no nature of their own and now
we'll be going on to the next four uh in
general when we speak about turnings of
the wheel uh we're thinking about
specific texts that typify that turning
of the wheel so uh we're talking about
uh the second turning of the wheel or
the medium turning of the wheel in terms
of the now uh those five characteristics
which typify the contents of the F the
second turning of the wheel and then
there are other uh works or other
subjects which typify uh which are which
are classic examples of the wheel and so
we've been through those been talking
about this uh when you talk about the
third turning of the wheel the job of
the third turning of the wheel was uh
people came up to Lord Buddha and said
what did you mean during the first and
the second turnings of the wheel so the
if you're going to talk about what is
the content or what are the uh classic
examples of of of subject matter that
comes up during the third turn of the
wheel well that would be discussions
just like the one we're having now which
is you know finding out what it is the
Buddha meant during the second turning
of the wheel and specifically during the
latter four of the five characteristics
which are typical of the second Turney
of the wheel so uh we'll be going now
into the third of those sections uh Lord
Buddha uh here when he's discussing the
latter four uh he will not be uh
covering all three of the groups that he
covered when he discussed the first of
the five right when he discussed the
thing the fact that things have no
nature he discussed all three groups of
uh that all three groups of uh objects
but when he gets to the second part
which is discussing those four
characteristics he's going to be uh
leaving out he's going to be skipping uh
one of those three groups uh and in in
Jetson's presentation jetona is going to
be quoting uh primarily that Sutra
called the Sutra in which the Buddha
explains his true intent during the
other all the other sutras which is
called do and then he's going to go on
to quote uh as necessary uh the great
forefather uh which is called the Great
Kimble right like the almost the Great
great Alid or the great uh the great uh
Master of the u m only school which will
be master of sa and then he'll also be
drawing in uh Master basab Bandu and
other great Masters as needed uh in his
presentation so that's where we're going
now
uh in the next uh in the next uh
presentation which is the louder four of
the five right uh which I I've already
mentioned that he's going to leave out
one of the groups he's not going to
treat one of the groups don't forget
that the first of the four is going to
be called uh looking into the fact that
the the that the arisal of things or the
beginning of things is not something
which happens of its own accord or by
definition so if you had to guess which
of the three groups uh might be left out
in this discussion which one do you
think it would
be
h
uh if we talk about uh a growing of
things which does not exist by
definition if I say I'm about to to
teach you what the Buddha meant when he
said things don't grow of their own
accord or by definition then which of
the three groups do you think he's going
to leave
out
huh uh you know we're talking about what
what could have be and uh at this point
you can kind of flip around and change
your mind if you
want how how many uh does that apply to
things don't have a nature of growing of
their own accord by
definition what are you doing so uh is
the Shen Wang things which are CA things
which are dependent is this the category
which you think should be left out when
we discuss that or the category that
should be left in when we discuss
that so if you take him by him
if you treat things which are dependent
by themselves things which grow from
other things by themselves is this the
one you'd want to concentrate on when
you talk about things not having a
nature of growing of their own accord by
definition oh so now I'm GNA ask uh with
regard to things that grow from other
things can you say that in the minor
only school no love
that it doesn't have uh any growing by
definition uh and if you say of the
other two categories oh these don't have
any nature of beginning of their own
accord or by definition uh is that okay
can you say that about
them
uh so can you use it for both or
not if you're going to keep uh lowering
the price when you sell this if you're
going to keep lowering the price when
you offer me the money for this thing
you know you should have told me from
the
beginning first you said we couldn't use
this expression towards us two now
you're saying maybe we can use it for
one of them and make up your
mind
it does uh use this expression
for uh uh what do you call constructs
and for this and he does not use this
expression uh refer to dependent things
of this expression so okay we'll
AG anyway uh jokes get better the hotter
it gets I mean when the weather is hot
then may we need more jokes
I think
down uh people have more and more faith
uh I know I didn't get it uh anyway
telling more jokes when the WEA is
hotter and keeps people away
okay Faith increases when the teaching
gets funnier
people are more likely to come uh and
leave the food
behind
spee
for uh will be beginning the quotation
from the Sut when explains Sut what he
meant when he explained when he spoke to
Sut and then they're going to be going
through first at the P top of page 19 he
specifies when he says dumble he's
kicking he's saying when I say things
don't have a nature of uh going of their
own accord or by definition then he's
kicking out the middle one and he's C on
the first one and the last one uh so
that's he's already uh agreeing with you
on that and then when he goes down he
goes through the he starts going down
through the four characters this is from
the the suture right and first he says
uh he starts going uh let me it says
things don't things don't start uh by
definition uh things don't stop by
definition uh things have been uh have
been peace from the beginning meaning
not self-existent from the beginning and
things have been uh things have been uh
Nana or or gone beyond right talked
about the other day and he says each one
begins to push the other one each one
triggers the next one so he says uh
because things don't have a natural
growing then they don't have a natural
stopping because they don't have a
natural stopping they don't have a
natural state of Peace because they
don't have a natural state of peace they
don't have natural state in each one
triggers the next one now how that is is
going to
go and we're only referring to conps
right now we're going to start uh this
explanation only refer to
con
foree
for
uh so uh again it's a process by which
each one of the four acces to justif
justification for the next one so each
one is TR in the next one so uh when we
say that uh things which are constructs
uh first of all they don't have any they
don't have any nature of having they
don't have any nature of being existing
by definition at all we've already
established that that was the first one
they don't have any nature of existing
by definition since they don't have any
nature of existing by definition they
cannot have a nature of having grown by
definition now whether or not they grow
are just not even approaching that
question since they don't have any
nature of of existing by definition they
cannot have any nature of having grown
by definition anything that hasn't grown
can't stop okay nothing that's grown
that hasn't grown could stop so needless
to say if you say this thing doesn't
have a nature of having grown by
definition then naturally that leads on
to the next one which is they don't have
any nature of having stopped by
definition uh when you and these two
qualities not having started by
definition not having stopped by
definition is that some kind of quality
that suddenly changed it used to be
different and now and now it's it used
to be one way and now it's another way
like the the growth and stopping of
things used to be existing by definition
and noway doesn't exist by definition
because Lord would have decided that now
it shouldn't exist by definition or
something like that it's not the way
that these two uh lacks of of self
nature are no they've been that way
forever ever since the beginning of time
you know that's called the suisha they
have been in a in a in a sense peace
peace meaning the state of non-existing
by definition the state of non-existing
self-existent they have been that way
forever they've been that way since the
beginning of the beginning that's what
the next one means sha means they have
been in a sense peace or a lack of
self-existence from the beginning and
it's not some kind of new story uh then
you take uh they have they are forever
gone beyond the state of a
self-existent uh birth self-existence
stopping they have always they've always
they've gone completely beyond the state
of having being born by uh by some kind
of by definition and stopping by
definition so if you take if you take
some sort of a threshold and you say
this is called grief okay this is called
grief in a sense or suffering in a sense
a self-existence stared and the
self-existence stopping are called grief
then all things all constructs have
forever passed beyond that grief they've
always been beyond that grief remember
that the toac is to pass beond grief
that's the last form so when Lord Buddha
says that passing Beyond grief doesn't
exist by definition either what he's
saying is that with regard to constructs
uh their stopping and their beginning
which has forever been not been existing
by definition and they are totally
passed beyond that state they have they
have gone beyond the state of
self-existence and in that sense they
are gone
beyond
uh now here the Buddha is making denial
after denial after denial saying this is
not true of this this is not true of
this this is not this this is not this
this ma this this ma this this La this
this La this what is he like what they
that what do you think he's talking why
is he C laugh doesn't have doesn't have
doesn't what's the very biggest root
crucial thing
uh that isn't
there uh you're correct very C actually
you're both kind of correct but you're
more correct and The crucial point is
yeah from the
beginning the batteries May last count
for 20 minutes but it won't keep
minute you got the main point it all
goes back to number one it all goes back
to the fact that things don't exist by
definition and because that first thing
doesn't exist by definition then the
fact that things goow Us by definition
and then the fact that things stop by
definition etc etc etc each one
Trigg so we have sort of a a logical
statement we say ah consider uh
consider constructs okay uh they don't
exist by definition because and can you
supply the reason
for
all I didn't translate the uh literature
correctly okay uh he says uh consider uh
constructs they don't they neither grow
nor stop they neither begin nor stop
by
and that's exactly what J says five
lines in bottom page 19 when he says uh
we have to POS it as a reason for the
fact that uh constructs don't neither
start nor stop by definition the reason
that we can put forth is that what it
still exist by definition
so if you say that for the reason that
they don't exist by definition they
don't start and they don't stop by
definition then you're implying that
they start and stop a different way well
what way would that be
uh how
say
give Michael that extra
that like you got this
extra how about we do it this way uh if
you say it this way they have no
starting and they have no stopping
because they are uh because they because
they exist by
definition uh so if you say a d what
happens to the to the to the starting
the
St there's no starting no
don't
chur
okay if you say that they don't have uh
because they don't
have because they don't exist by
definition they don't have starting and
stopping now if they did have starting
and stopping then
what
if I go around and hold up the stick and
say this stick has its own starting and
this has unstopping then in effect what
am I important
gr you
could and that's exactly how put it
present looks
like uh if it started by uh if it if it
had if it did have a nature of growing
and
stopping we're following a particular
line of reasoning where he said because
they aren't that they have they they do
that and if they were that they'd have
to be young on the way and in general
what you said is true but in this
particular line of reason we can't we're
not going that don't don't wand off to
those fields out
there
uh generally speaking in the minority
school any kind of study any kind of
stud would have to be such that it was
by
Def so the implication here is that if
something didn't have a starting and if
something didn't have a stopping which
existed by definition wouldn't have a
St that's what he's been kind of
searching
around uh so if you put it into a
logical statement of necessity you have
to say that if something has a starting
and if something has a stopping then it
has it must by necessity have a starting
and a stopping ex by defin
uh so when you asked me uh just before
if there could be any other kind of uh
starting or stopping if it weren't
starting or stopping by definition
you're kind of getting your answer
here it's a it's a it's a necessity both
ways it's a k both ways uh if it is in
this school in this school if if
something has starting and stopping it
must be a starting and stopping which
exists by definition if something has a
starting stopping which Exist by
definition then it can have a starting
and stopping and if it doesn't have a
starting can't
have
uh now we keep having this little uh you
know vignettes where we have
little uh where you and I discuss
something and then we always have to go
back to the book and say well here's
where the book says that so we have to
go back to the Authority or the basis
and saying I'm not just making this up
it's not some little conversation this
is exactly ex to be the next Point book
and if you want to see where that little
last viette came from it was page 19
Fifth Line from the bottom up to the
second line from the bottom and in there
the Buddha says exactly what we just
said
uh now if we divide uh if we talk about
things now let's not talk about things
that don't exist okay let's just talk
about things that do exist
so so if we posit if we if we restrict
ourselves to things that exist and then
we further make the uh the requirement
that this thing should not have a
beginning or stopping or where do we end
up
then
yes uh you are right and what you just
said is correct because you were
thinking in terms of the three groups
but if we don't say in terms of three
groups if we divide all existing things
I know you guys have studied durah
Elementary logic and Elementary you know
logical forms so I know you're going to
know the answer to this if you divide
all existing things into two categories
what are the two
things
yeah where where did we end up after we
kicked out one of
those and that's exactly what the text
says page 19 second line from by the way
I think I just said good I think this is
J uh and it says what is that
thing what is it what is that thing
which is devoid of starting and stopping
what what are those existing things
which don't have starting stuffing oh
okay unchanging things things which have
not been caused or
created uh where are we going to put
constructs we're going to put them on
the ca side the UNC
I'm um they're not
changing
don't forget we've been talking about
these four characteristics right we we
finished the one we on the last four uh
no uh starting by itself no stopping by
itself and then uh peace from the
beginning meaning not something from the
beginning and then the fourth one we
remember was uh it nature is to be total
Nana it nature is to be totally Beyond
grief and one meaning of this is that
it's totally beyond all negativities
meaning all mentally Afflicted things
okay so you can you can interpret the
word uh grief as meaning all mentally
afflictive things all things having to
do with mental Affliction uh can be def
can be grief can be described that way
then having a nature of being Beyond
grief can be described as having a
nature of being Beyond those things
which are involved with mental
Affliction mental Affliction are
involved with mental Affliction now
among the two kinds of objects changing
and unchanging where are you guys going
to put those all those mental Afflicted
things
uh now don't forget you put the
constructs in the unchanging stuff and
then you went put the uh mental
Afflicted stuff in the changing stuff uh
is there any mental fed stuff that has
to do with the conp
yeah
wait a minute where construct is staying
with those changing stuff and the
unchanging stuff
what's I don't quite like it if you say
you know that this uh changing mental
stuff is going to come live in the house
of the unchanging construct that make up
your
mind
anyway if uh if uh the if the face has
uh all unchanging things and then
suddenly it gets uh something out of out
of whack and something because the nose
is like changing but the face is
unchanging it's not really cute make
every
constant good
doct
what
didn't you guys already agreed that
things having to do
withal
so you have to say that uh in a sense
because uh one is changing and one is
unchanging that constructs living in the
unchanging Camp right are totally free
of uh mentally Afflicted things which
are changing things so in a sense they
are devoid they are gone beyond they are
a piece of those things and now he's
using those same wording to describe
constructs being gone beyond mentally
Afflicted things or or passed Beyond
mentally Afflicted things or peace a
state of Peace which is free of mentally
Afflicted
things
foreign
yeah so uh we've been describing how
constructs are free of the of all four
Gods right we have these four guys which
are birth which starts uh birth which
exists by definition ending which exists
by definition peace state of being in
peace state of Peace which exists by
definition and then state of like going
gone beyondness which Exist by
definition and the first two were easy
you saw how a a a an arisal which exists
by definition and a stopping which Exist
by definition could not apply to
constructs but now we have to examine
can these last two apply to constructs
and and peace means uh a state of Peace
which is free of mentally Afflicted
things so it's true you can say about
constructs that they are in a state of
Peace meaning that they are free of
mentally Afflicted things and you can
say of con constructs as well that they
are in a state of Nirvana meaning
they're in a state of having transcended
or having gone beyond mentally Afflicted
things so in that sense uh the the lud
guys don't apply to
constructs uh does that make sense does
that okay the lud don't apply to con
right uh when they exist
by because doesn't EX defition no uh
this
uh he says it's true whether you add by
definition or
not it's true of constructs that they
are a state of Peace which is devoid of
U mentally Afflicted stuff and it's also
true of Concepts that they are a state
of Peace which is deployed of uh
mentally Afflicted stuff which exists by
definition
for
uh but it's my my fault I think the
translation uh you have to add the word
AR not to the first two they do not have
a nature of uh staring by definition
they do not have a state of nature of
sto definition but in the latter two
he's saying they are a state of Peace
which is devoid of mentally Afflicted
stuff and in the fourth one is they are
the state where you have gone beyond
mented stuff so the second two are in a
way a positive expression of a negative
thing okay uh they are a state of Peace
which is devoid of of mentally affected
things and then they are uh a state of
transcendence of going Beyond mentally
Afflicted things so that was I think
is that okay any problem that okay okay
sorry for the
confusion something to uh when you say
peace you mean and by the way in tibetan
the word peace also means uh death or
stopping you see so when you say peace
or stopping it means a state of not
having that thing anymore state where
that bad thing has stopped and when you
say Transcendence or nirvana in tibetan
the indication is gone beyond or
transcended or cast Beyond a state where
the thing is suffering or or uh grief
which here means rly took the things
so you can also describe that that
triggering process that that progression
uh in that way so uh because they don't
start by because their starting has no
nature of existing by definition and
their staring has no nature consist by
information and because of that now you
can go this way they they are in a state
of Peace which is beyond uh I'm sorry
they are in a state of Peace in which
you have stopped right jok and tobet and
she she you are in a state of Peace
where you have stopped with those M
Afflicted things and then you are in a
state where you have gone beyond the
grief of the mentally Afflicted things
so you can say it that way too you can
describe this progression that
way
and and so now again I'm going back to
the text to give you scriptural
Authority for the little conversation we
just had okay so you go back to page uh
19 uh second line from the bottom and
it's here that uh they
identified uh the peace for example and
they identified the grief for example
and here it says uh peace and uh a to a
total uh natural sort of a natural Nana
it says here uh you can identify those
now as being page two sorry line two
page 20 as being uh gong which means all
of those things which have to do with
mental Affliction so peace meaning an
absence or a rest in peace of the uh of
the mental Afflicted things and then uh
passing transcending being transcending
going Beyond Nally infed things and
here's the actual scriptural backup for
that little conversation
uh before I promised you uh we go in two
groups two three groups right we left
out one of two one of the three groups
and we promised that we would go through
the remaining two groups we have now
completed going through the constructs
you can close the case on the constructs
okay and now we're moving on to Yong
which is emptiness in the mar school and
we have to describe uh emptiness in
terms of the latter four of the five
characteristics that came up during the
second ter right so here we
go
uh then uh first we're going to get the
the quotation from Sutra where in budha
explains what he meant in the suus and
then you're going to get the explanation
by J C of what that means so uh that's a
long story it goes from line really goes
from line two or three on page 20 down
to the next and last line and uh gu we
don't have to go through that Cal cation
directly word by word what we'll do is
we'll go to jeton ca's explanation of of
what that thing
means
foree
uh when we discussed the concepts uh
because it it was already something that
description number one applied to right
description number one is what existing
by definition right not existing by
definition right out of the five
non-existing by definition so we said
that there was a progression that was
triggered by the first one all through
the end of the time so not existing by
definition Trigg is not growing by
definition Trigg is not stopping by
definition um means that it is peace or
uh rest in peace of the of certain
things and then it was going Beyond
those things uh but now when you talk
about emptiness itself you don't have to
have the first one you will not have the
first one you can't say of emptiness
itself that it is not something which
exists by
definition uh so we go straight to the
second one okay it's not it's not a
fstep process it's a four step process
you
so uh the the place where we step off
from stepping off place is not going to
be the same not stepping off from it
doesn't exist by definition now we're
stepping off from it doesn't have any
nature of Starting by
definition is that
okay
I oh yeah yeah okay
it's
uh it's with number two that we start
the things that don't apply
to how about your Quiet Ones is this
okay
everybody knows that of the three groups
two of them are do exist by definition
only one of them does it by definition
did you guys everybody knows
that we we we B this catch
yesterday uh are your problems all okay
move ahead now two of the two groups do
exist so you can't you can't use a
characterization number one with regard
to
everybody clear on
that uh the latter two characterizations
which is that it it has reached the
state of Peace uh wherein the mental
afflictions have rested in peace right
and then uh the fourth one which says
they have gone beyond or transcended
transcended the state of of grief uh
these two are easily applicable to
emptiness these two are easily
applicable to Y okay to to transl why
because uh obviously emptiness itself is
obviously devoid or a state of Peace
which is wherein the mental everything
related with mental afflictions has has
ended or stopped rest in peace right
right and then the fourth one obviously
uh Emptiness is something which is
passed Beyond and gone beyond a state of
grief in the sense of grief as uh
something they don't apply
to
for
uh now just a comment going back in uh
discussing especially the fact that uh
emptiness itself does not have uh those
uh qualities of Beginning by definition
right called it we did these two right
we do these two yet and this one doesn't
apply and so in discussing whether or
not uh emptiness itself has the quality
of of starting U by by definition or
ending by definition right in discussing
that Joka is going back to the original
quotation from the Sutra in which the
Buddha explains himself in this true
inten sutras which covers most of page
20 which takes up most of page 20 and in
there there are some very uh difficult
Expressions inban when they got
translated from deeton uh they are
difficult they become difficult
Expressions so Jensen comp is trying to
help you out with some of the difficult
expressions in the sudra when he gets
onto the subject of why these two don't
apply to emptiness itself and there's an
expression called tap
and uh DBA in English means unchanging
as you know t means uh in English like
uh
self-standing uh independent uh stands
on its own something like that uh and
and these difficult Words which means uh
the time of the unchanging unchanging
and the time of the self-standing
self-standing uh the first one J says
refers to all the time that came before
so the time of the unchanging of the
unchanging the time of the unchanging
unchanging means all the time that came
before us and the time of the the time
of the self-standing of the self-
standing or the time of the independence
of the independence refers to all the
time which is to come so these two
expressions are referring to all the
time they came before and all the time
which us to
come
what's his got to do that with proving
that these two characteristics don't
apply to emptiness right asking for a
better translation y
meaning
fore
I asked for a little explanation of Yong
because I don't want to keep saying
emptiness when he keeps saying Yong
because now we got to the point where
he's saying Yong D is emptiness right uh
and it it means total existence but that
doesn't it just doesn't seem comfortable
to me I think construct is good for good
down and things that are depending is
okay for sh but I I don't like this
saying total existence so I asked him is
there a literal explanation why it's
called total existence why is emptiness
he says well let's go back into that mon
door and I'll sneak out something that
will help you understand how to
translate it into English uh Duke the
word existence here means if we talk
about a water pitchure the minute a
water picture begins to exist the minute
a water piture comes into existence then
every single thing to do with the water
picture all its parts everything about
the water picture every single tiny
piece of the water picture is
automatically entirely totally something
that is not self-existent so upon the
state of existence all the totality of
the days is is not self-existent that's
what total existence means okay so how
to translate into
English
total totally
there tell we'll say totality okay
something like that we'll figure out
okay when I say total you know what I'm
talking about okay which is emptiness
okay so now we go back to the point he
says where where did those two weird
Expressions come in to explaining why
totality doesn't have uh these two
characteristics it says uh the first
expression is from the beginning of the
beginning right from from forever and
the second expression is for forever
meaning Hereafter so what does that got
to do with proving that uh totality
doesn't have these two characteristics m
if you say if you start talking about
forever either way then you're already
into the category of unchanging things
aren't we okay so the manying you're
you can't say anything about changing
things about it uh starting and stopping
are words that only apply to changing
things so that's why we can immediately
uh upon start when the reason the Su is
starting to talk about these two
characteristics from the beginning and
forever after uh then the reason is that
they're they are talking about the fact
that totality meaning emptiness doesn't
have any nature of starting or stopping
anyway so you don't have to you know go
into much detail you know it's no big
deal to explain why they don't have
starting and stopping by definition so
obviously those two characteristic
characterizations don't apply to uh
tality to emptiness
itself
uh generally speaking in in dealing with
Buddhist terminology you can use uh a
llama's explanation of the literal
meaning of the parts of the components
of the word to help you understand how
to translate the word but he says be
very careful about thinking that uh the
literal explanation of the pieces of a
word is always a definitive uh
understanding of what the word means
because it's not there'll be many cases
in in many Expressions where if you try
to use the literal components of the
word uh the word that you end up with is
not going to be descriptive of all the
things that are called with that word
all the things that are named that word
so be careful with that C thank
you totality is in is is the state of
being empty okay because totality is the
state of emptiness with then it can
never change it will never change and we
cannot speak of it in terms of growing
and St so because it is it is the state
of emptiness because it's iMed with the
state of emptiness then what we call
totality uh cannot be described in terms
of starting or stopping so those two
characterizations of it don't apply
to
uh and the latter two to repeat are easy
to understand I don't have to go into
any big story about it uh if you take uh
if you take the word peace or having a
state of Peace meaning a state where
something has been put to rest uh then
you can describe emptiness or totality
as easily as being uh something which
does not have the state of mental
Affliction mentally afflicting things it
is a state of Peace where that is absent
and also if you describe it in terms of
being having gone beyond or having
transcended the state of mental
Affliction then it's easy to see why
emptiness itself has transcended the
state of mental
affliction
uh you may uh somebody might raise a
question where did Jet Cop come up with
this interpretation of those two
difficult phrases from the from the
beginning the beginning and from the
from the forever forever you know where
he come up with understanding how did he
identify them correctly as meaning all
the time pass and all the time to come
uh yesterday uh we mentioned or a couple
days ago he mentioned a China a Chinese
uh
commentary commentary from by the chinan
and he says that's J is saying that's
where I got that interpretation from of
of the CP word that's that's where I
that's where I have learned that that it
means this thing otherwise they're very
weird words the time of the changing of
the unchanging and the time of the self
standing of the self standing and I got
my interpretation from that particular
cont
uh now there comes an objection somebody
raises a question uh he says Master
wrote a book called A okay this is a
compendium on higher knowledge okay and
then in that text
uh Master ASA said that these four
qualities right not having any uh uh
starting by by by definition not having
any stopping by definition being in a
state of total peace from the beginning
and being in a state of transcendant or
having gone beyond grief okay he said in
that text this person who's raising this
this issue says that Master uh asanga in
that book said that those four
attributes apply to all three
groups okay and not just two of them so
what's that all
about
here's how the question comes up in the
quotation from the
ab in the ab then Master says um it's
because uh the Buddha said that uh
constructs don't have a nature of
existing by definition and because uh
things which are dependent or cause
don't have a nature of growing and
because uh those things which are uh
because totality doesn't have a nature
of being ultimate it's because of those
three he says that the Buddha said that
things don't have a nature of existing
by definition things don't have a nature
of growing things don't have a nature of
stopping things are total peace from the
beginning and Things Are
the state of transend so in
the master is saying because this is
true of these three groups that's why
the bud spoke about those four the
flatter four
characteristics so don't they play all
three
fore
uh this is a little bit difficult for me
okay uh when we talked about uh when we
talked about constructs we talked about
how all five triggered each other right
we talked about with constructs with
regard to constructs it's true that they
don't have any existence by definition
and then that easily flowed on to each
of the other four uh when we talked
about uh totality which means emptiness
right uh then we skipped the first one
because it's it is true of it it's not
true of it that it doesn't exist by
definition and then we went to the other
four uh now when you get to shenan with
things which are dependent or things
which are caed it's impossible to speak
of it in terms of not having
a a a nominal sort of growing
and a and a relatively true sort of
growing uh in a parent gr and in a
parent stoping you know anomally uh in a
nominal sense uh it does have those
things so it's to point that out that uh
master of saga is talking about all
three groups because what he means to
say about the second group is that uh
you have to realize that it that it does
have a nominal it does have a nominal
stopping so the point of him mentioning
it here the second group is only to to
because he wants to talk about it in
terms of having a nominally existent
growing and anomaly existing stopping
and the other and and other things
applying to it as well so what when he's
talking about the second group he's now
talking about remember how we left out
the first we did all five regarding to
constructs then we left out the one that
we had to leave out when we talked about
uh emptiness and now he's saying uh
Master s is saying and you can also use
these with regard to the second group
but you have to adjust them too now also
you have to change it to Nally grally
sto like I think that's the point that
was difficult for
me
fore
for
uh just what I said before okay let's
start again I told him it wasn't really
that clear like over again so just what
I said before okay uh jet kaapa is
trying to further elucidate why the
Buddha in the book where he in the Sutra
where he explains the inous sutras did
not uh say that these five applied to
things which are dependent or things
which are caed okay and he says G says
let's leave the right now okay don't
worry about it right now we'll come back
to it why is it jeta says that Buddha
didn't choose to to uh describe uh the
second category which is things that are
caused or things that are dependent in
terms of being those four things right
why didn't the bud to do that well first
of all they you can't say they don't
have a nature of uh of of growing by
definition why because they do have a
relatively uh real or a nominally real
uh nature of growing by Def of growing
and if they have that then that growing
has to Exist by definition and that that
growing is a growing by definition in
this school
okay and if they have a stopping which
is a relatively true stopping then you'd
have to say that they do have a stopping
which exists by definition so you
couldn't say about them that they don't
have a stopping which Exist by
definition or that their stopping
doesn't exist by definition you couldn't
say that because their stopping does
Exist by definition in this school
that's why the Buddha in didn't apply
the first two characterizations to
things which don't I'm sorry things
which depend on their causes and
conditions now what about the latter two
right one is a state of peace which is
avoid of mentally Afflicted things one
is a state of transcendence of going
Beyond things which are have to do with
mentally Afflicted things and here G
says if you think about it uh most of
the things which are changing most of
the things about our current world
around us which are caused uh can't be
described as things that eventually will
have to eliminate within our being like
uh the world that you see around you
most of the parts of you although not
all and I ad not all okay uh if I say
not all but I can I can say that most of
the changing things in your experience
your the place you live you yourself the
different parts of your body and mind
are all things that eventually you'll
have to eliminate and give up and move
to a pure virgin right so in that sense
those things cause things or at least
the great majority of cause things in
our experience
are not such that there peace in the
sense of being deed mentally Afflicted
stuff and they are not such that they
are Transcendence in the sense of having
gone beyond mentally Afflicted stuff so
buha couldn't use any one of those four
characterizations when he spoke about
changing things the second C now I think
he's going to go on to the up
down
fore
uh now if you want the scriptural
authority to back up what I just said
about why uh those four characteristics
are not
applied actually the way they stated in
is said they were not what the Buddha
was talking about when he spoke about
those four okay the way they said inter
uh changing things are not what the
Buddha was talking the reason why they
are not what the Buddha was talking
about when he said those four things is
that uh what I just said uh that those
four reasons I just gave you and if you
want to find a scriptural Authority for
that uh we're starting uh down in uh the
end of page 21 uh going up to the page
beginning of page 2 22 and what it says
here is especially
uh
okay uh five lines up from the bottom 21
where it says do at this point they're
saying why wasn't it changing things
that the Buddha was talking about when
the Buddha talked about those four
characterizations right and then he
answers himself and he says well first
of all with regard to the first two
which is they don't start by definition
and they don't stop by definition uh
it's a double negative here the problem
the reason the Buddha didn't
characterize changing things that way is
that they are not something which is not
dependently
R that's why he didn't use those first
terms about it why because they are not
something which is dep which is not
dependently Rising meaning they are
something which is dependent Rising
that's why the bu couldn't say about
them that they don't have a starting and
stopping which Exist by definition
because at this school their starting
and stopping doesn't exist by definition
okay and then with the latter two it's
exactly what I just told you page 22 uh
second
line where the Buddha
says means the vast majority which is a
my right um implying that there are uh
things which change which
it for which the latter two descriptions
would be accurate it would be acceptable
but because the vast majority of them P
CH are are uh involved or are included
into the group of things that we call
mental afflictions or the results of
mental Affliction or the cause ofal we
call all these together that's why I've
been saying mentally Afflicted things
and not mental afflictions it's a very
important distinction so they belong to
the mentally Afflicted side of stuff
okay and that's and that's why because
most changing things in our experience
belongs to the Mally Afflicted side of
stuff most uh Buddha didn't they were
not what the Buddha was thinking of they
not what the Buddha had in mind when he
said those last two things oh things are
at peace from the beginning things are
in a state of rest from the beginning or
things have transcended uh grief uh
meaning mental Affliction mentally AFF
stuff from the beginning okay and that's
why those four uh were not that's why
the Buddha didn't have changing things
in mind when he spoke about those point
I hope he gets back to
the that
could
is waiting in to grab you waiting in
ambush
uh it says be careful later when you
translate all the stuff in English we're
going to get to this uh part which talks
about
simaima Sima literally means the latter
two words uh meaning the latter two
expressions meaning the latter two of
the force so don't forget it you know
when you get to this later and you're
translating English and you run into
this little expression that says the
latter two words it means the latter two
characterizations meaning in a state of
total the beginning and uh totally
Beyond uh I think you better put a
little star next to that expression that
says uh the vast majority of cause
things have are involved with mentally
effed
stop because I think you might be having
some questions arising in your mind
right now about that
St did you put your
stars
what did master mean the in the comp of
knowledge when he said those four
character characterizations apply to all
three of the groups what did he have in
mind when he said that well I take you
back to the other day when we were
talking about how these three groups
didn't have any nature you know one
didn't have any nature of such and such
another didn't have any nature of such
and such another didn't have any nature
of such and such let's go back to that
let's grab that those ideas those
Concepts that we had the other day and
shove them into the future and bring
them here and let's let's try to use
them
for do you think there's any
application got any ideas about any
application to the Pres to the present
question let's
go have to one
appes applying distinctly to
which so the same thing you apply see
which apply to find out one of them
doesn't get at
all I
didn't
of you mean so the four
characterizations do apply to someone
and some he's try to
show why why was it the master why was
it the master seem to be
these four characterizations do require
to all three groups and what is it about
the other day we were talking about the
three groups relating correspondingly to
three kinds of a lack of nature lack of
nature having characteristic lack of
nature having
nature ultimate right what what are
those two do those three have any
applications this question why did
Master say that those four
characterizations all
three
reach we P
out
uh don't you remember this morning when
I asked you about the expression
existing by definition nonexisting by
definition and I asked you how many of
the three groups could this apply to and
how many should not apply to and then
you guys went into this long explanation
some people said two and some said three
uh he said uh most people agree with me
that you could say of only one of the
groups right that it didn't exist by
right and then you agreed that you had
to say the other ex by definition but
then some of you were flirting with the
idea that some of them did all three
perhaps didn't exist by definition you
remember and you remember why you
thought that and anything to say about
could that apply to
what because the said that things don't
exist by Nature that have qualities that
start and have ultimate nature and those
two things correspond directly to the
three attributes of the Mind the SCH
so so if the said that doesn't have any
nature then did he mean then it could be
said
that
okay
fore
so let's forget uh constructs and let's
forget totality en right let's
concentrate on things that are dependent
and I understand your point uh it's well
taken uh perhaps the fact that uh the
wording not having a nature might refer
to in general not having nature of
existing by definition and that that
might apply it's said to it seems to be
applied correspondingly to all three of
them so in that case it seem to apply to
things which are caused and uh in the
middle turning of the wheel in the
second turning of the wheel it is true
that the Buddha was talking about things
not existing by
definition uh I lost the rest anyway so
let's just talk about things that come
from causes uh let's just decide whether
or not uh they can be in any way
characterize as non-existent by
definition uh how do you think we can do
that in what sense could that apply to
them uh I'll give you a clue you know
okay trying to make it easier uh how is
it that the expression doesn't have a
nature of growing right how is it that
that applies to fa
in
is that just
idea uh she said remember that the
meaning originally back in the old days
right uh of characterized
uh cause things as not having a nature
of gr meant not having a nature of gr
without the causes and condition so does
that have any application here does that
help you also that's one and then the
other one is they don't have they don't
grow from the CES that you
think
yeah yeah I
got uh I just uh brought up that second
point because I knew Lo would sooner
later start teaching you that black book
which is a monastic text subject because
it concentrates so much on that point
but right now you can pack it up and
just leave way you know leave it
aside it's not it's not
a
he's saying that Christie was on the
right TR uh Christie's point was that
when they talked about things having
causes uh depending on their causes as
not having a nature of being of starting
they meant not having a nature of
starting without depending on their
causes and conditions so if you
interpret from the mind only School
point of view the wording of Lord Buddha
in the secondary of the wheel when he
said things don't have a nature of
existing by definition if you interpret
those words with regard to things that's
depend growing things right as meaning
they don't have a nature of growing uh
without uh depending on the causes and
condition that's how you take what it
means when the Buddha said things don't
exist by definition when he referred to
changing things in the second turning of
the wheel well then this quotation in
the compan of higher knowledge by Master
begins to make sense because then you
can say um the up those category of
things which are changing or depending
on their causes that they don't have a
that they don't have a nature of
Starting by definition they don't have a
nature of stopping by definition and
they are in a state of total peace from
the beginning and they are transcended
from that thing because in that case the
word existing by definition now doesn't
mean what it usually means in the
minority school it rather means they
don't have a nature of existing by
definition in the sense they don't have
a nature having come about without
depending on causes and
conditions
must got all
that the
definition the definition is different
what when you're talking about changing
things has a totally different
meaning
don't
fore
uh I can't read on mine but there is
this thing in B that says about you've
had a communicating form form which
communicates to inent or state of
mind
about which indicates the State of Mind
person has it and I was just checking
her communicating form
there and I noticed that it seem to
communicate some uh didn't get 100% of
what I said about that the way mus
translated it so I just wanted to check
and make
sure I think Roy got it though if he
looks at his communicating
part
did
so uh he says uh if you clarify the
reasoning with regard to each one of
those if you clarify each one carefully
you say well this is what this one means
in this case this is what this means in
this case this is what this one means in
this case each of the three
groups
so jent is saying when master in his
compendium on higher knowledge said that
those four
characterizations do apply to things
which are caused what he really had in
mind was uh they don't have a a nature
of growing by definition when you take
the words by definition to mean they
don't have a nature of growing uh
without the causes okay and and when you
say uh they don't have a nature of
stopping by definition what you mean is
they don't have a nature of in this case
only with the sh only with things that
are dependent on their that they don't
stop through any nature which is not
dependent on causes and conditions okay
and then and then the other two are easy
too so all four uh Master what he has in
mind really is a reinterpretation for
caus things of what it means to consist
by definition and then it all clears up
then all
four then then changing things could
have been what the Buddha had in mind
when he spoke those four things
also are we okay on that
guy
okay could you say way Say by their
definition alone to rule out their
puzzles say they don't grow by
definition by the definition alone they
don't just in and of themselves they
need something
else
that's okay but you got to be careful
because in general the expression uh
they have a way of which exists by
definition is something they do accept
in general with regard to changing
things so if you adjust that word to
saying uh they have they have a nature
of going by
themselves they might actually accept
that if they thought that you meant by
Def they thought that you meant by those
words by definition they don't demand
out things that change so that's a
that's why we
don't
good thinky
to when you came up with that thing that
by definition could Me by themselves you
were try to sneak
off
so if on one hand you say that uh the
original Sutra only applied those four
character characterization to two groups
and then you get to and and and Master
has applied to all three groups if you
don't go ahead and reinterpret
uh what existing by definition means in
one case as being distinct from the
meaning of existing by definition in the
other case then you have a then you have
a
problem case is closed let's
go
foree
uh so we've been talking about these
three lacks of a nature we started out
talking about how constructs don't have
a nature and we talked about how
costumes don't have a nature then we got
talking about happiness doesn't have a
nature certain natures and then we were
describing how this applied to them or
this didn't apply to them and all that
but you know you didn't really describe
what is a k what is a construct you know
what does it mean when you say depending
on others you know what does it mean
when you say totality you know what are
those three groups we didn't really get
to that so here finally after the fact
he says uh we're going to get a a a a
section in which Jessa uh goes into
identifying what those three groups are
for us because even though you and I
have been talking about these three
groups and sort of come to an
identification of them to our
conversation if you think about it in
the text so far he hasn't really
formally gone into the explanation of
this so here we start off page 22
uh about seven line down from the top
and uh we're going to identify what
those three groups are attrib they're
called attributes right what those two
attributes
are uh in identifying those three groups
and what they are and what it means to
be one of those three groups the biggest
castle the worst Castle is what does it
mean to be a that's a
real uh things that depend on other
things you know things that go from
other things we are wearing them we are
eating them we are sitting on them that
doesn't take genius to to
disc
if you can
describe uh if you tackle the problem
first of what are constructs uh then it
gives you a big head start on
understanding what the third group is
meaning totality mean Infamous so uh if
you tackle uh the difficult one first
then you have a inent say place two on
uh you have a you know you have a good
starting off point uh then you can then
you can tackle the subject of what is
the inate so it's a lot easier to tackle
number three once you've tackled number
one uh I'm just again laying out for you
the road that we're going to travel um
tomorrow
morning
do you remember I told
you I think better that star
t
it might pop into your mind you know you
might I actually Po in my mind I don't
know about you but when he got to the
point and said the vast majority of CA
things are tied up with mental
Affliction or mental afflictive things
then I started to think and he said you
might start to think all those beautiful
things in bu paradises all those
beautiful parts of a Buddha that are
changing and so if you get into
statistics you know well which one
outnumbers the other you know are the
changing things that are fantastic or or
Buddha is um are they more numerous or
are the changing things which are um
some soric or or or mentally Afflicted
more numerous let's get into a head
count uh who's going to come out ahe
what do you think can we say vast
majority
for
he says it's very helpful to think that
way that's a very true statement it's a
very it has great benefit for you to
remind yourself of the truth of that and
so I'll allow you to stick your head
into that door but please don't call the
way in
there
fore uh when Papa uses the wording vast
majority uh what he really has in mind
is listen because we're studying by
definition uh the very fact that we're
sitting here studying these things means
that uh we are in the condition of
people who have not reached there yet
you know we are not people sitting in a
Buddha Paradise uh you know thinking
about these things and and and our our
normal experience is from the point of
view of somebody who has not yet made
great progress along the path so it's
what we call called the original
condition there's a word in that we call
the original condition or the the
initial condition of samsar meaning we
are in the state of what we call the
initial condition the vast majority of
what we experience the vast majority of
things around us the vast majority of
person who has not yet entered the path
and made great progress on the path
those things are either mental
afflictions or tied up with mental
afflictions and it's not the point Jess
is not trying to say that statistically
uh on the whole
that there are more subaric things than
enlightened things that's not that's not
the case and that's not what the word
vast majority means here vast majority
means here that in the original
condition of our world of our lives uh
the vast majority of things are either
mental
FS
this is jessa's style and you can apply
the style to other situations you know
if you understand what's going on with
this word vast majority then you'll
understand what's going on whenever he
does that because this is his style he's
talking about it from this point of view
I forgot to translate one thing he said
uh uh also not only are those things yet
to be reach for us but they are also
beyond our capacity of understanding or
imagining so when he says vast majority
he's also saying that the vast majority
of what you can even grasp or or imagine
uh the things that you can imagine most
of them are mental afflictions or have
to do mental we are incapable at the
initial level of even imagining those
things in the real so so we can say vast
majority in that case in that
sense
we
the